<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Welcome to My World]]></title>
  <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-29T22:56:59+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://beingasysadmin.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Deepak M Das]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Mongo Discovery Method in MCollective]]></title>
    <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2012/11/29/using-mongo-discovery-method-in-mcollective/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-29T21:48:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2012/11/29/using-mongo-discovery-method-in-mcollective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve been playing around with  <strong><em>MCollective</em></strong> for the past few months. But this time i wanted to try out the <code>Mongo</code> discovery method. The response time was quite faster for the <code>Mongo</code> discovery method. So i really wanted to try it out. Setting out MCollective Server/Client is prettyl simple. You can go through  my previous <a href="http://beingasysadmin.wordpress.com/2012/09/10/setting-up-mcollective-with-activemq-in-ubuntu-12-04/">blog</a>. Now we need to install the <strong>Meta</strong> registration plugin on all the MCollective Servers. Just Download and Copy <a href="https://github.com/ripienaar/mcollective-plugins/blob/master/registration/meta.rb">meta.rb</a> in the MCollective registration plugin folder. In my case, i&#8217;ve Debian based machine&#8217;s, so the location is, <code>/usr/share/mcollective/plugins/mcollective/registration/</code>. This will make the metadata available to other nodes.</p>

<p>Now add the below three lines into the <code>server.cfg</code> of all the MCollective server&#8217;s.</p>

<pre><code>registration = Meta
registerinterval = 300
factsource = facter
</code></pre>

<p>Now install the <a href="https://github.com/ripienaar/mcollective-plugins/blob/master/agent/registration-mongodb/agent/registration.rb">mongodb registration agent</a> on one of the nodes, which will be our slave node.. Do not install this on all the nodes. There is a small <a href="http://projects.puppetlabs.com/issues/16447">bug</a> in this agent. So follow the steps mentioned <a href="http://projects.puppetlabs.com/issues/16447">here</a> and modify the <code>registration.rb</code> file. Now install mongoDB server on the slave node. Also add the below lines to the <strong><em>server.cfg</em></strong> in the slave machine.</p>

<pre><code>plugin.registration.mongohost = localhost
plugin.registration.mongodb = puppet
plugin.registration.collection = nodes
</code></pre>

<p>Now restart the mcollective service. If we increase the log level to <strong>debug</strong>, then we can see the below lines in the <code>mcollective.log</code>. This indicates that the plugin is getting activated and it is receiving request from the machines, whose fqdn is shown in the below line.</p>

<pre><code>D, [2012-11-29T15:51:34.391762 #12731] DEBUG -- : registration.rb:97:in `handlemsg' Updated data for host vagrant-debian-squeeze.vagrantup.com with id 50b650d4454bc346e4000002 in 0.0027310848236084s
D, [2012-11-29T15:50:05.810180 #12731] DEBUG -- : registration.rb:97:in `handlemsg' Updated data for host ubuntults.vargrantup.com with id 50b650c0454bc346e4000001 in 0.00200200080871582s
</code></pre>

<p>Initially, i used the default <code>registration.rb</code> file which i downloaded from the github. But it was giving me an error <code>handlemsg Got stats without a FQDN in facts</code>. So don&#8217;t forget to modify the <code>registration.rb</code></p>

<p>Now go connect to mongoDB and verify that the nodes are getting registered in it.</p>

<pre><code>$ mongo
 MongoDB shell version: 2.0.4
 connecting to: test
 &gt; use puppet
 switched to db puppet
 &gt; db.nodes.find().count()
 2
</code></pre>

<p>So, now both my master and slave have been registered into the mongoDB. Now in order to use the <strong><em>Mongo Discovery Method</em></strong>, we need to install the <a href="https://github.com/puppetlabs/mcollective-plugins/tree/261ac8ef8433df98f3a9179778182807b916bc46/agent/registration-mongodb/discovery">mongodb discovery plugin</a> and also we need to enable the <strong><em>direct addressing mode</em></strong>. so we need to add <code>direct_addressing = 1</code> in the <code>server.cfg</code> file.</p>

<p>Now we can use the <strong>&#8211;dm</strong> option to specify the discovery method.</p>

<pre><code>$ mco rpc rpcutil ping --dm=mongo -v
  Discovering hosts using the mongo method .... 2

  * [ ========================================================&gt; ] 2 / 2


  vagrant-debian-squeeze                  : OK
    {:pong=&gt;1354187911}

  ubuntults                               : OK
        {:pong=&gt;1354187880}



  ---- rpcutil#ping call stats ----
            Nodes: 2 / 2
      Pass / Fail: 2 / 0
      Start Time: Thu Nov 29 16:48:00 +0530 2012
  Discovery Time: 68.48ms
      Agent Time: 108.35ms
      Total Time: 176.83ms

$ mco rpc rpcutil ping --dm=mc -v
  Discovering hosts using the mc method for 2 second(s) .... 2

  * [ ========================================================&gt; ] 2 / 2


  vagrant-debian-squeeze                  : OK
        {:pong=&gt;1354188083}

  ubuntults                               : OK
        {:pong=&gt;1354188053}



  ---- rpcutil#ping call stats ----
            Nodes: 2 / 2
      Pass / Fail: 2 / 0
      Start Time: Thu Nov 29 16:50:52 +0530 2012
  Discovery Time: 2004.24ms
      Agent Time: 104.28ms
      Total Time: 2108.51ms
</code></pre>

<p>From the above commands, we can see the difference in the <strong><em>Discovery Time</em></strong>.</p>

<p>Now for those who want <strong><em>GUI</em></strong>, <a href="http://www.devco.net/">R.I.Pienaar</a> has develeoped a web gui called <a href="https://github.com/ripienaar/mco_rpc_web.git">Mco-Rpc-Web</a>. He has uploaded a few <a href="http://www.screenr.com/user/ripienaar">screencasts</a>, which will give us a short demo on all of these.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vagrant: Make Virtualization Easier]]></title>
    <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2012/11/26/vagrant-make-virtualization-easier/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-26T18:21:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2012/11/26/vagrant-make-virtualization-easier</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>Vagrant</em></strong> is a light weight virtualization tool, build over Oracle&#8217;s <code>VirtualBox</code>. It&#8217;s completely written in ruby and it&#8217;s very easy to install and configure. The only dependency is <code>VirtualBox</code>. Once VirtualBox is installed, we can either use <code>RubyGems</code> to install <code>Vagrant</code> or we can get the installer from <a href="http://downloads.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a>.</p>

<p>I prefer ruby gems, So</p>

<pre><code>$ gem install vagrant
</code></pre>

<p>That&#8217;s it, it will install vagrant. Now we need to get the base box. Vagrant uses the base boxes to build the VM&#8217;s. We can download the base boxes from <a href="http://www.vagrantbox.es/">Vagrant Boxes</a>. we can directly use the url to create the boxes, but it&#8217;s alwasy good if we have a downloaded copy of the base boxes.</p>

<p>Basically we need to follow just 3 steps. <em>add</em>,<em>initialize</em>,<em>up</em>. So once we have the base box just add the base box.</p>

<pre><code>$ vagrant box add new_box_name our_downloaded_basebox_file

example,
$ vagrant box add mybox precise32.box
</code></pre>

<p>Now just do a <strong>vagrant init</strong> to create the <code>Vagrantfile</code>. This is the main configuration file. If we go through the <code>Vagrantfile</code>, we can see a bunch of options like port forward, provisioning, setting network and so on. If only one vm is required, then we just have to add the <em>new_box</em> name which we created at the <code>config.vm.box=</code> option int the <code>Vagrantfile</code>. And <strong>vagrant up</strong> will start the VM.</p>

<p>But one of the most important feature of <strong><em>Vagrant</em></strong> is it suports multiple VM&#8217;s over one single box. But we have to define those VM&#8217;s in the <code>Vagrantfile</code>. Below i&#8217;ve defined two VM&#8217;s in my <code>Vagrantfile</code>, also comment out <strong>config.vm.box=base</strong></p>

<pre><code>config.vm.define :ubuntu do |ubuntu_config|
     ubuntu_config.vm.box = "precise32"
end
config.vm.define :puppet do |puppet_config|
     puppet_config.vm.box = "precise32"
end
</code></pre>

<p>Where <em>ubuntu</em> and <em>puppet</em> are the name of the VM&#8217;s. And <em>precise32</em> is the name of the the box which i&#8217;ve created. Now, <strong>vagrant up</strong> will start all the VM&#8217;s. But we can mention the name to start a specific VM. Like <strong>vagrant up ubuntu</strong>. It will start only the <strong>ubuntu</strong> VM.</p>

<p>Provisioning is another important feature of Vagrant. We can use <strong><em>puppet</em></strong>,<strong><em>chef</em></strong> and <strong><em>shell</em></strong> scripts to bootstrap the vm&#8217;s. I saw <a href="https://twitter.com/mitchellh">@mitchellh&#8217;s</a> talk at <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UTQQggVx4sI&amp;feature=BFa&amp;list=PLV86BgbREluVFB73Wwqp_tCbw5Z9TMLX1">PuppetConf 2012</a>, in which he mentioned about how to create a <strong>Fully Automated Puppet Master</strong> using the <strong>shell</strong> provisioner. I&#8217;ve tried this out using a shell script that will install puppet master and genrate the ssl certificates. It&#8217;s working fine, soon i will post it here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Riak With Logstash]]></title>
    <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2012/11/25/using-riak-with-logstash/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-25T20:34:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2012/11/25/using-riak-with-logstash</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the last few days i was playing around with <code>Riak</code>, a distributed database. It&#8217;s very simple to configure and use and offcourse it supports MapReduce. I wanted to try out the <strong><em>map reduce</em></strong>, and since <strong><em>Logstash</em></strong> has a plugin to write data into riak, i decided to use it with logstash on an Ubuntu 12.04 machine.</p>

<p>Installing <code>Riak</code> is very simple, it has only one dependency.</p>

<pre><code>$ apt-get install libssl0.9.8
</code></pre>

<p>Once the dependencies are being installed, we have to download and install the deb package of Riak from its website. The below link is for 32bit OS.</p>

<pre><code>$ wget http://downloads.basho.com.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/riak/CURRENT/ubuntu/lucid/riak_1.2.1-1_i386.deb

$ dpkg -i  riak_1.2.1-1_i386.deb
</code></pre>

<p>Once Riak is installed, go to <code>/etc/riak</code>, where the config files are available. We can change the name of the riak node by editing the <code>vm.args</code> file. By default Riak will listen to <strong><em>127.0.0.1</em></strong>, but we can change this by editing <code>app.config</code> file.  In order to use enable https enable, we need to uncomment the https section in Riak core config. We also have to mention the path of the server key and certificate. Riak comes with a build in Admin console, which currently has very minimal functions. It shows the status of the riak nodes as well as the members in the riak ring. To enable this, open the <code>app.config</code>  go to <strong><em>riak_control_config</em></strong> and change the <strong><em>enabled,false</em></strong>to <strong><em>enabled,true</em></strong>. The user name and password can be mentioned in the userlist option.</p>

<p>If we have multiple machine we can create a riak cluster using riak-admin tool. Currently i&#8217;ve only one machine with Riak installed.</p>

<p>In Riak, data&#8217;s are stored in <code>Buckets</code>. A <code>Bucket</code> is a container and keyspace for data stored in Riak, with a set of common properties for its contents (the number of replicas, or n_val, for instance). Buckets are accessed at the top of the URL hierarchy under <strong><em>riak</em></strong>, e.g. <code>/riak/bucket</code>.</p>

<p>Now we have Riak machine, listening on port port <strong>8098</strong>. Now we need to configure <code>Logstash</code> to send the data to the <strong><em>riak</em></strong>. This is very simple because logstash has an output plugin which can directly write to riak.In the output section of logstash config file, add the riak output plugin.  It should be like this,</p>

<pre><code>riak {

  bucket =&gt; bucketname

  type =&gt; typename

  nodes =&gt; ["riakserverip","8098","riakserverip","8098"]

    }
</code></pre>

<p>In the nodes section we have to mention the riak node ip&#8217;s. Since i&#8217;ve only one riak node, i&#8217;m mentioning the same ip twice.That&#8217;s it, now we need to start logstash, then logstash will start writing data into the bucket which we mentioned in the conf file.There is one good GUI for Riak called <a href="https://github.com/basho/rekon">rekon</a>. Just get the source code from <em>github</em> and edit the <strong><em>install.sh</em></strong>and change the ip mentioned in to the ip which riak listens to and execute it. Now we can access the GUI using the below url.</p>

<pre><code>http://riakserverip:8098/riak/rekon/go
</code></pre>

<p>Now testing the <strong><em>Map Reduce Function</em></strong></p>

<p>This is one of the main features of Riak. For example i&#8217;m going to write a <em>map reduce function</em> that will display all the keys in my bucket that has the keyword <strong><em>mylinux</em></strong>, which is the hostname of my machine. This function will return the <em>key</em> as well as the <em>number of occurrences</em>. Below is a simple <em>MapReduce</em> function.</p>

<pre><code>"inputs":"mybucket",
"query":[{"map":{"language":"javascript",
"source":"function(riakObject) {
var m = riakObject.values[0].data.match(\"mylinux\");
return [[riakObject.key, (m ? m.length : 0 )]];
}"
</code></pre>

<p>To execute the map reduce function, execute the following command,</p>

<pre><code>curl -X POST http://192.168.1.173:8098/mapred -H 'Content-Type: application/json' -d '{
"inputs":"mybucket",
"query":[{"map":{"language":"javascript",
"source":"function(riakObject) {
var m = riakObject.values[0].data.match(\"mylinux\");
return [[riakObject.key, (m ? m.length : 0 )]];
}"}}]}'
</code></pre>

<p>The above command will return all the keys which has the keyword <strong>mylinux</strong> along with number of occurrences.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hiera-Http And Riak]]></title>
    <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2012/11/24/hiear-http-and-riak-vagrant/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-24T23:48:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2012/11/24/hiear-http-and-riak-vagrant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past few days, i was playing with <code>hiera-puppet</code>. I strongly wanted to use <code>hiera</code> in my puppet modules. Yesterday i was going through <a href="http://www.craigdunn.org">craigdunn&#8217;s</a> blog, there i saw his new blog post about the <code>hiera-http</code>,a Hiera back end to connect to any HTTP RESTful API and return data based on a lookup. <code>hiera-http</code> is available as a rubygem or from <a href="http://github.com/crayfishx/hiera-http">craigdunn&#8217;s</a> Github page. In his blog he has clearly explained how he uses <code>hiera-http</code> to query data from <code>couchdb</code>. Since i&#8217;m a fan of Riak, i wanted to try the same from Riak.</p>

<p>I used the <a href="https://github.com/basho/riak-ruby-client">riak-ruby-client</a> to pass my json data to Riak. Below is a simple ruby script which i used,</p>

<pre><code>    #! /usr/local/bin/ruby
    require 'rubygems'
    require 'riak'

    client = Riak::Client.new(:host =&gt; '192.168.1.120', :http_port =&gt; 8098)
    bucket = client.bucket("hiera_bucket")
    deb = Riak::RObject.new(bucket, "Debian")
    deb.content_type = "application/json"
    deb.data = { "db_name" =&gt; "testdb", "db_pass" =&gt; "P@ssw0rd" }
    deb.store
</code></pre>

<p>where <strong><em>hiera_bucket</em></strong> is the name of the Bucket and <strong><em>Debian</em></strong> is the key.</p>

<p>Now we need to create a <code>hiera.yaml</code>,</p>

<pre><code>    :backends:
      - http

    :http:
      :host: 192.168.1.120
      :port: 8098
      :output: json
      :failure: graceful
      :paths: /riak/hiera_bucket/Debian
</code></pre>

<p>We can test the working using hiera cli <code>hiera -c hiera.yaml db_name</code></p>

<p>As per the <code>hiera-http</code> dcumentation, we can use the facter variables, so  the path can be <code>:paths: /riak/hiera_bucket/%{operatingsystem}</code>. For those who wants a gui for Riak, i prefer <a href="https://github.com/basho/rekon.git">rekon</a>. It&#8217;s very simple to install and configure, also we can edit our values directly using this.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FPM - A must have Packaging Tool]]></title>
    <link href="http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2012/11/08/fpm---a-must-have-packaging-tool/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-08T14:48:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://beingasysadmin.com/blog/2012/11/08/fpm&#8212;a-must-have-packaging-tool</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>fpm</em></strong> is a wonderful tool for building our own packages. It&#8217;s very simple to use. I&#8217;m a qmail user, since our <a href="http://www.deeproot.in/deepofix">deepOfix Mail Server</a> is built on that. So in many situations i&#8217;ve to compile the qmail from the source along with custom patches. And one main thing about qmail is that it need a bunch of files in the <em>control</em> folder for its working.</p>

<p>Since we are automation freaks, we even wrote a <em>puppet</em> module for qmail. But then i came to know about the <strong><em>fpm</em></strong>. Since it supports pre and post scripts, i can automate so many things not only creating the control files, but also adding necessary run scripts to run as a <em>runit</em> service.</p>

<p>fpm is very simple to install:</p>

<pre><code>  $ gem install fpm
</code></pre>

<p><code>fpm --help</code> will give us a good description about the options.</p>

<p>So in my case, i&#8217;ve already compiled my patched Qmail into <code>/var/qmail</code> folder. I&#8217;ve a few dependencies <strong>(libssl-dev,openssl,zlib1g-dev,libldap2-dev)</strong> and also <strong>runit</strong>, because i will be using the post script option to start runit services automatically.</p>

<p>My prescript will just add the necessary Qmail users.</p>

<pre><code> addgroup --system nofiles
 addgroup --system qmail

 adduser --system --home /var/qmail/alias/ --shell /bin/false --no-create-home --ingroup nofiles alias
 adduser --system --home /var/qmail/ --shell /bin/false --no-create-home --ingroup nofiles qmaild
 adduser --system --home /var/qmail/ --shell /bin/false --no-create-home --ingroup nofiles qmaill
 adduser --system --home /var/qmail/ --shell /bin/false --no-create-home --ingroup nofiles qmailp
 adduser --system --home /var/qmail/ --shell /bin/false --no-create-home --ingroup qmail qmailq
 adduser --system --home /var/qmail/ --shell /bin/false --no-create-home --ingroup qmail qmailr
 adduser --system --home /var/qmail/ --shell /bin/false --no-create-home --ingroup qmail qmails
</code></pre>

<p>My post-script will just populate qmail control files like <code>defaultdomain</code>,<code>locals</code>,<code>rcpthost</code> and also create a runit service for <strong><em>qmail-send</em></strong> and <strong><em>qmail-smtpd</em></strong></p>

<p>Now we just need to build the debian package.</p>

<pre><code>$ fpm -s dir -t deb --before-install preinst.sh --after-install postinst.sh -d "runit (&gt;= 2.0)","openssl (&gt;= 1.0)","libssl-dev (&gt;= 1.0)","libldap2-dev (&gt;= 2.4)","zlib1g-dev (&gt;= 1.2)" -n qmail /var/qmail/
</code></pre>

<p>where <code>-s</code> is for <em>source</em>, <code>-t</code> for <em>package type</em>,<code>-d</code> for dependencies and <code>-n</code> for name of the package. There are som many other options also which includes desription etc. But for the time being i&#8217;m using very basic options for testing. The above command will build a debian package for me. That&#8217;s it pretty simple.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
